Hi so we finished the tutorial.
You did it! You learned the program
in about an hour.
That's pretty amazing
if you think about it.
What you have done is
you've written lines of code.
You've run that code.
You've made things animate.
You've made different colors.
You've taken those first
steps in creating your own
software. And now there's
just this huge world of
possibilities bursting
open to you.
When I leave you here
you're going to have
a couple of choices.
You can go back to
the code editor and
work on what you were
making more. And there
will actually be a new option
there. To share what you
made. You can share
what you made with friends
and save it to come back
and work on it more later.
I'm also going to leave you
with a bunch of hopefully
helpful links, places you
can go to to learn more about
programming with processing.
Other resources to take this
further. One of the things
you probably would most
want to do is go to the processing
website and actually download
processing which is an
application that you run
on your computer. It has many
more features. Many more
examples that you can
take a look at. So there's also
a link below to the processing
forum where you can go and
post and ask questions. I'll be
checking the forum and trying
to answer your questions
as well as many other
members of the processing
community. So hopefully we'll
get to make more of these
tutorials in the future. So
I'd love to hear your feedback
about what was helpful and
what was not helpful. And
I look forward to seeing
all the things that people
make. And more people
using processing and asking
questions and inventing stuff
with code. So thanks again
for being here. I had a
great time. I hope you did
too. And I'll talk to you soon.
Okay. Bye-bye.