Hi. How are you? My name is Dan. Welcome.
If you're here, which hopefully you are
because you're watching this video,
you're here to learn Programming.
Hopefully you're here to learn Programming
for the very first time.
This is going to be a tutorial.
It's designed for you to take about
an hour to complete.
There's going to be lots of stuff
happening in it.
I'm going to talk. Hopefully not too much.
I'm going to draw pictures and diagrams
over here on this whiteboard.
Sometimes this video is going to
get a lot smaller and there's going to be
text below me, and things drawn
to the left of me over here.
We're going to look at Programming
in the context of the visual arts.
What does it mean to write software
to do the things that you often do
with your hands, with paper, with pencil
with paint? Could you use a computer to
create drawings? To create animations?
To create images? This is what we're
going to look at.
So, before we get started with the actual
nuts and bolts of learning to code,
let's take a moment to look at a range of
projects -- things that have been made in
recent years with computer programming
for the visual arts.
This is Strata #3 by Quayola.
Quayola is an artist working in London.
This animation combines computer generated
images with video of a cathedral in Rome
to create a fantastic new reality.
In his own words, he is investigating
improbable relationships between
contemporary digital aesthetics, and
icons of classical art and architecture.
This is Oasis by Yunsil Heo.
She is a media artist working in Seoul.
Oasis is an interactive installation.
By moving around the sand,
small pools are created
where new software creatures are born and live.
This is Replica by Alex Vessels and Jeff Howard.
Alex and Jeff are interactive artists and designers
working in New York. Replica is
an interactive dance performance that
uses live image processing to explore how
the awareness of time and captured images
affect self-perception.
It was projected onto a 120 foot
video wall in New York.
This is unnamed soundsculpture by
Daniel Franke and Cedric Kiefer.
Daniel and Cedric are media artists
working in Berlin.
This animation is a moving sculpture
created from the recorded motion data
of a live dancer.
These animation and installation projects
are just one way that visual artists
are working with code.
More traditional design areas such as
map design, brand identity, and logo design
and illustration are transformed through
designers writing their own code.
This is the Dencity Map by
Fathom Information Design.
Fathom is a design studio in Boston.
This map uses circles of different sizes
and colors to visualize
population density in a unique way.
Larger, darker circles show areas
with fewer people. While smaller brighter
circles highlight crowded cities.
By glancing at this map we quickly get
a sense of how some cities and countries
are more densely populated than others.
This is the logo for the MIT Media Lab
created by the Green Eyl.
The Green Eyl is a studio based in Berlin.
The identity system can be used
in different ways and in many contexts
including the lab's website, business cards,
and in any other media.
It forms a beautiful identity that is
synonymous with the Media Lab's
approach to the ever changing
nature of technology.
In addition to the kind of work
we're looking at already,
there's sculpture, fashion design,
architecture, products, jewelry,
pottery, much much more.
What does writing software have
to do with these physical objects?
Everything.
It's an area of exciting and emerging possibility.
New technologies make it possible
to print objects. For example, it is now
possible to design a ring in software
and print it in plastic or metal.
Let's look at three final examples before starting
to learn how to code.
This is the D.dress software by
Mary Huang. Mary is an entrepreneur
and designer working in New York.
D.dress is a program written by Mary
that allows a user to sketch a dress and
it automates the pattern creation.
It re-imagines the classic little black dress
by changing the relationships between
manufacturing, the designer, and the wearer.
The Textile Room was created by the
architecture studio P-A-T-T-E-R-N-S,
founded by Georgina Huljich
and Marcelo Spina. Georgina and Marcelo
are architects working in Los Angeles,
The Textile Room is an experimental
media space where carbon fiber textiles
are augmented with a video colleague.
This is Cell Cycle by Nervous System,
a design studio founded by Jessica Rosenkrantz
and Jesse Louis-Rosenberg.
Jessica and Jesse are entrepreneurs
and designers living in Boston.
Cell Cycle is a program that allows
people to design their own jewelry
and then 3D print it.
All of these projects we just looked at
are created with a software environment
called Processing. Processing is a way
to program invented by artists
and designers to be used by
artists and designers.
Processing is for making visual media.
It focuses on writing programs to draw
create animation, and to build
interactive experiences like video games.
Hopefully you're going to have a good
experience learning to program
and I'm already having fun just talking to you
even though I don't really know
who you are yet cause you're not here.
There's a camera there. Okay.
I'll talk to you later. Bye.